<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Established test in order to the security of His Majesties sacred person, and government, and the Protestant religion against the malitious attempts and treasonable machinations of Rome.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A38667</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229328</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11987440</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11987440</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51961</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A38667)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51961)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1008:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Established test in order to the security of His Majesties sacred person, and government, and the Protestant religion against the malitious attempts and treasonable machinations of Rome.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.N. for Jonathan Edwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Test Act (1673)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51961:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51961:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Eſtabliſhed Teſt, In order to the Security of HIS MAJESTIES Sacred Perſon, AND GOVERNMENT, AND THE Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>AGAINST The Malitious Attempts and Treaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Machinations of <hi>ROME.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Nemo ſibi naſcitur,</l>
               <l>Partim Patriae, &amp;c.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRIMAT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R</hi> Jan. 3. 1679.</p>
            <p>Geo. Thorp. R<hi rend="sup">mo</hi>. in C. P. &amp; D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guilielm. Archiep. Cant.</hi> à Sacris Domeſticis.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. N.</hi> for <hi>Jonathan Edwin,</hi> at the three <hi>Roſes</hi> in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet,</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:51961:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51961:2"/>
            <head>THE Eſtabliſht Teſt.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HAT a Tempeſt ſhould we have had, if this Black <hi>Italian</hi> Cloud had bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken over our Heads? Never was <hi>Hurricane</hi> ſo double charged, with Death and Deſtruction: It would certainly have Rain'd Fire and Fag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gots, and all Inſtruments of Cruelty, upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Heads of Poor <hi>Proteſtants.</hi> But <hi>GOD</hi> have the Praiſe, That we are in hopes to ſee it not only Blow over, but that the Storm is likely to fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Heads that raiſed it. Some of theſe treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Dealers, who have dealt ſo very treacherouſly with us, are already <hi>fallen into the Pit which they had digged for Others,</hi> and are enſnared in the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51961:3"/>Works of their own Hands; and it is to be hoped for the Reſt, That <hi>their violent dealing will fall upon their own Heads;</hi> for He who is Truth it ſelf, in whom we truſt, whoſe we are, and whom we ſerve, has aſſured us, That <hi>Wicked and Bloodthirsty Men, ſhall not live out half their Dayes;</hi> for he who is the God of all Mercy, <hi>abhors the cruel and decoitful Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a Concern of ſo common and univerſal Near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I cannot conceive any Perſon ſo little or incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in a <hi>Nation,</hi> but ſince he muſt participate and have a ſhare in the common Happineſs or Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes that ſhall happen; he muſt alſo have a Right, if not a Duty, to endeavor to do what ſervice he can to the <hi>Publique:</hi> Every Mans <hi>Oar</hi> may, and ought to be in the <hi>Boat,</hi> to preſerve her from ſinking; and though poſſibly I may value my endeavors in this little <hi>Scrole,</hi> as cheap as any can deſire, yet the good Intention of it being the only thing that can give it a Recommendation, that may alſo procure it Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don; and if it be demanded why I write? 'tis an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Not to increaſe the Croud of <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> which at ſuch Times fly about the Streets like Chaff before the Wind; ſo that one is obliged to take ſome Pains to find the Wheat; which ſome able and induſtrious Hands have winnowed from the Droſs; but it is perfectly out of <hi>Charity,</hi> and for the Information of ſuch who will not be at a greater Charge than ſuch a <hi>Trifle.</hi> And therefore I do not pretend to Inſtruct the great Managers of the Affairs of <hi>State;</hi> or to meddle with the <hi>Needle</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs</hi> of the <hi>Publique</hi> Bottom; 'tis dangerous med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with the <hi>Helm</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> even ſometimes for the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:51961:3"/>
               <hi>Publique Pilots;</hi> I am no <hi>Dictator</hi> of <hi>Politicks,</hi> or Pretender to give Unerring <hi>Rules</hi> for our future Settlement, or preſent Security; but a Plain, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, Well-meaning <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> who heartily Honor my <hi>Prince,</hi> Love my <hi>Church,</hi> and Wiſh well to my fellow <hi>Subjects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to manifeſt that I am ſo, I will endeavor in ſhort to ſhew to thoſe of my own <hi>Sphere,</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Danger under which we lie, whil'ſt we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted with theſe concealled <hi>Semenaries</hi> and <hi>Jeſuites;</hi> the probable Way to Detect and Diſcover them, notwithſtanding their <hi>Protean</hi> Faculties of Diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, Perjury, and Putting on ſo many Shapes; and the great <hi>Intereſt</hi> that every Man has, to do his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, to clear the Nation of ſuch Secret <hi>Scorpions,</hi> as Poyſon both Mens Souls and Bodies.</p>
            <p>It is in vain for us to hope to be free from <hi>Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes</hi> and Convulſions of <hi>State</hi> ſo long as theſe Men of <hi>Tempeſtuous Principles</hi> are continually ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their Fireworks in our very <hi>Intrals;</hi> the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy</hi> is fitly reſembled by the dreadful <hi>Aetna,</hi> or <hi>Veſuvius,</hi> which take Trace ſometimes with the neighbouring Plains for many Years; but when the ſulphurious Maſs of their <hi>Intrals,</hi> is recruited, then do they break out in horrid <hi>Flames,</hi> to the terror of the Country round for many Leagues; which they ruine and cover with barren <hi>Pamites</hi> and Aſhes; thus will the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> when one of their Plots is dico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and prevented, give us a little breathing; not out of any <hi>Charity</hi> to us, or <hi>Remorſe</hi> in their own <hi>Conſciences,</hi> but to make us more ſecure till another <hi>Deſign</hi> is ripe for <hi>Execution:</hi> We have often through
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51961:4"/>Gods goodneſs eſcaped their treacherous <hi>Mines,</hi> even when they were ready to Play; but who is able to ſay, We ſhall always be ſaved by <hi>Miracles?</hi> if the <hi>Red Sea</hi> be divided for our ſakes, we muſt walk through it; if we will eſcape to a Shoar or Safety, ſomething we muſt do, and endeavor to promote our own Peace, Safety, and Security.</p>
            <p>It cannot be doubted, but the <hi>Roman Dragon</hi> has been and ever will be induſtrious and vigilant to regain this <hi>Heſperian</hi> Garden of <hi>England,</hi> which in times paſt was wont to yield him ſuch Plenty of <hi>Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Fruit,</hi> that one of the Popes was uſed to ſay, That <hi>England</hi> was <hi>Putens inexhauſtus,</hi> A Spring of <hi>Treaſure,</hi> which could never be drawn dry; and if the <hi>Italian</hi> Gulph, which they Term the <hi>Apoſtolick Chamber</hi> could not do it, he had ſome reaſon to ſay as he did. We need not give our ſelves much pain, to trace this <hi>Leviathan</hi> the crooked <hi>Serpent,</hi> in all his windings and turnings, by which he has endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd, to wrap and embrace us again in his painted, but mortal <hi>Folds:</hi> There has paſt no <hi>Princes</hi> Reign ſince the Reformation, but what has been plagued with the pernicious <hi>Counſels,</hi> or miſcheivous <hi>Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems</hi> of theſe Sons of <hi>Matchiavel:</hi> and they have all ways been endeavouring either by open <hi>Cruelty,</hi> or ſecret <hi>Conſpiracies,</hi> to re-eſtabliſh the <hi>Roman Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny</hi> among us.</p>
            <p>To theſe inveterate Enemies of our <hi>Peace,</hi> were our <hi>Anceſtors</hi> obliged for all the Treaſons and the Wars of <hi>Queen Elizabeths</hi> Reign: <hi>Catena,</hi> who writ the Life of <hi>Pope Pius the Fifth,</hi> gives a full Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of the ſecret Counſels of that <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>King</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:51961:4"/>of <hi>Spain,</hi> and attributes all thoſe conſequent Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> to the warm Zeal of that <hi>Pope,</hi> to reſtore us to the <hi>Catholique Faith.</hi> To theſe we owe, that moſt barbarous, helliſh, and deteſtable Deſign of the <hi>Gunpowder Treaſon,</hi> in the beginning of <hi>King James</hi> his Reign over <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that upon which they had grounded ſo much confidence, and which they intended ſhould be one deciding Blow for all, proving an Abortive <hi>Monster;</hi> and the long-fancied <hi>Monarchy</hi> of the <hi>Weſt,</hi> to which the ambitious <hi>Spaniard</hi> had made ſo many years court in vain, coming to decline into a mighty <hi>Nothing;</hi> and that <hi>Nation</hi> having little left of all their aſpiring Graſpings after <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire,</hi> beſides the <hi>Pride</hi> that too commonly attends it; there was a neceſſity of changing the meaſures of their <hi>Policy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>Spain</hi> being by the help of the <hi>Inquiſition,</hi> the Cruelties of the Duke <hi>d' Alva,</hi> and the Aſſiſtance of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> diſmembred of ſo great a Strength as the ſeven <hi>Maritine Provinces</hi> of the <hi>Neather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands;</hi> and the fatal <hi>Eighty Eight</hi> having clipt her Pinions of Power at Sea; <hi>Portugal</hi> revolting to the Family of <hi>Braganza;</hi> they judged, that even <hi>Hope</hi> of Aſſiſtance from ſo crazie, maimed, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jointed a <hi>Crown,</hi> was a vain Impoſſibility. <hi>France</hi> was full of Civil Broils, occaſioned by the Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Houſe of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and the <hi>Princes</hi> of the Blood to the <hi>Regency,</hi> during the Minority of <hi>Francis the Second,</hi> and <hi>Charles the Ninth;</hi> and in danger of becoming totally <hi>Hugonot</hi> it ſelf, had not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51961:5"/>the Bloody <hi>Veſpers</hi> of St. <hi>Bartholomew</hi> in the Year 1572. by the <hi>Pariſian Maſſacre,</hi> as they thought, let out the moſt dangerous and Feavouriſh <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> Blood in the <hi>Body;</hi> and after that, had it not been reſcued from that danger in the <hi>Head,</hi> by the more than <hi>Roman,</hi> the <hi>Roman Catholique</hi> cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages of <hi>Clement</hi> and <hi>Ravilliac,</hi> by whoſe Aſſaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating Hands the Two <hi>Henries,</hi> the <hi>Third</hi> and <hi>Fourth</hi> fell; ſo that little hope of help was to be expected from that Quarter, to regain <hi>England</hi> to Obedience to the <hi>Catholique Faith of Rome. Germany</hi> was at too great a diſtance, and too much <hi>Lutheran,</hi> and compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of too many jarring and perpetually jealous <hi>Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts,</hi> to expect any Succour from <hi>Ratisbonne;</hi> nor was it well able to defend it ſelf from the furious Shock of the Warlike <hi>Guſtavus</hi> King of <hi>Sweden;</hi> who in probability had he lived any conſiderable time, would have made good the <hi>Anagram</hi> of his Name, and changed it to <hi>Auguſtus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Circumſtances of Affairs, and the poſture in which <hi>Europe</hi> then ſtood, obliged the Sons of limping <hi>Loyola,</hi> to put off the <hi>Lyons</hi> Skin, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to play the <hi>Fox;</hi> and to try if <hi>Art,</hi> and <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> would not repair what their unſucceſsful <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> and improſperous <hi>Arms</hi> had in vain attempted. And now the <hi>After-game</hi> they had to play for ſo great a <hi>Stake,</hi> was to be managed with their moſt refined Skill: from henceforward <hi>Divide &amp; Impera</hi> muſt be the <hi>Word;</hi> the ſecret <hi>Spring</hi> that muſt move the mighty <hi>Machine,</hi> by which they were to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat our overthrow. All their <hi>Arts</hi> were uſed to ſow Diſſentions, Sects, Schiſms, Fears and Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51961:5"/>among us; and by pretending a danger and fear of <hi>Popery,</hi> really to make the way eaſie to intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce it. The firſt crop which they reaped, and the early Earneſt of their future <hi>Harveſt,</hi> was the loſs of the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> by which the <hi>Proteſtant In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terest</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> ſuſtained a moſt dangerous Blow, and the <hi>Catholique</hi> received a conſiderable acceſſion both of Power and <hi>Proſelytes:</hi> for by this time, they had ſo infected <hi>England</hi> with Fears and Jealouſies, that King <hi>James</hi> could not get a Parliament to part with a Penny of Money for the Relief of his Son-in-Law the <hi>Elector,</hi> unleſs he would pawn his <hi>Crown</hi> and Prerogative for it. Nor could his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor King <hi>Charles</hi> do any thing towards Reſetling that unfortunate <hi>Prince</hi> in his rightful <hi>Inheritance;</hi> nor in concluſion to preſerve his own.</p>
            <p>Fluſht with this lucky <hi>Hit,</hi> and the ſucceeding loſs of <hi>Rochel,</hi> they now reſolve cloſely to follow the Blow, and purſue their point; and by making the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Party in <hi>England</hi> appear good and loyal Subjects, zealous for the <hi>Crown,</hi> and oppoſite to the <hi>Factious</hi> of the ſeveral <hi>Sects,</hi> they were reſolved by this one <hi>Artifice</hi> to ruine the <hi>Heretiques,</hi> by their own Diviſions: for by this means the <hi>Papiſts</hi> began to appear quiet and innocent, and not only ſo, but <hi>Loyal</hi> Subjects and Friends to the <hi>Crown:</hi> this they knew would diſarm the Penal <hi>Laws</hi> in force againſt them, of their uſual ſeverity; and that would at once increaſe the number of their own <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> and that of <hi>Diſſenters</hi> too; and whilſt many were recalled whom the fear of Perſecution had ſtagger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the <hi>Romiſh Religion,</hi> the <hi>Indulgence</hi> which
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51961:6"/>was ſhewn them, gave ſuch Apprehenſions and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larms of the growth and fear of <hi>Popery,</hi> that it aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the number of Diſſenters, and gave a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourable pretext to the <hi>Factions</hi> and <hi>Diſloyal</hi> among them to manage their <hi>Deſigns</hi> with the greater <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For this unmerited Clemency of our <hi>Princes,</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally tender of the Lives and Fortunes of their Subjects, ſo long as they ſaw no appearance from them, but of Innocence, Kindneſs and Loyalty; they conſtantly perverted to this ingrateful uſe, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly to inſtil a <hi>Jealouſie</hi> into the Minds of their <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Subjects, of their diſ-affection to the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion:</hi> inſinuating that the Suſpenſion of the Penal Laws in force againſt <hi>Roman Catholiques,</hi> was the effect of the Princes inclination to <hi>Popery.</hi> Now the <hi>Court</hi> was certainly making a tack towards the Coaſt of <hi>Italy,</hi> and it would not be long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they came to an Anchor in <hi>Tyber:</hi> for what could make it more clear and manifeſt, than the Kindneſs, as well as Indulgence which was ſhewn to thoſe of that <hi>Perſwaſion?</hi> This deadly Poiſon, thus ſweetned and guilded over, went down with the Querulous and Credulous Multitude of diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and was not a little forwarded by thoſe Factious and Diſcontented Promoters of the late <hi>Rebellion,</hi> as the moſt ſerviceable Engine, to batter down both the <hi>Crown</hi> and the <hi>Church.</hi> What unconceiveable pleaſure was it now for theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> to ſtand behind the <hi>Scene,</hi> and prompt both Parties, to Act the bloody <hi>Tragedy</hi> which they had compoſed? Without all doubt,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51961:6"/>this intoxicating <hi>Jealouſie,</hi> made great Numbers of innocent and undeſerving Perſons ſtagger into the other <hi>Extream;</hi> and the extraordinary fears and cry of Popery, drive Men ſo far from that, that at laſt by the violence of the increaſing Storm, they threw over-board all their <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and in a manner all <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had not that great Man <hi>Archbiſhop Laud,</hi> been one of the <hi>Jonahs</hi> that was firſt heaved over the Decks to allay the <hi>Tempeſt,</hi> we had certainly had then a full diſcovery of the whole Deſign; as moſt fully appears by the Letters now lately Printed of Sir <hi>William Boſwell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The ground Deſign of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in the Reign of King <hi>Charles the Firſt,</hi> &amp;c.</note> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ambaſſador in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> to the <hi>Archbiſhop, Andreas ab Habernfeilds,</hi> the <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> to the King, and his Majeſties An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; together with a particular of the whole De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Papiſts, who are therein by Name men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, to ruine the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Archbiſhop,</hi> and with them the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> by Civil Wars, which were begun by their contrivance in <hi>Scotland.</hi> But it was too much the Intereſt both of the Papiſts and <hi>Rebels,</hi> to ſuppreſs thoſe Papers, and the further diſcovery of thoſe Deſigns by his haſty death; for had he lived to compleat the Diſcovery, all the After-game of both Parties, had been counter-plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and though poſſibly the <hi>Rebels</hi> knew nothing of the Deſign till after his death, and that his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers fell into their hands; yet, then they were too far imbarqued in the <hi>Civil Wars,</hi> to ſound a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat, and to proclaim themſelves Murtherers, for taking away the <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> as a Papiſt, whoſe Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence would thereby have been fully vindicated,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51961:7"/>and their Guilt made notorious, to the ruine of all their <hi>Eſteem</hi> with the People, and the utter confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their Ambitious Deſign of <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> and erecting a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> upon the Ruines of the <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that nothing can be more clear and evident than this; That from the ſubtil Practices of the <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites,</hi> thoſe Diverſities in <hi>Opinion,</hi> and Differences in Practice among Proteſtants, received their En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, if not their <hi>Riſe</hi> and <hi>Original:</hi> and while every new <hi>Sect</hi> pretended ſtill to out-do others in the Purity of <hi>Reformation,</hi> and a further eſcape from the Superſtition of the <hi>Romiſh Babylon,</hi> they were all made Inſtrumental to undo the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion; and a thorough <hi>Reformation</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the Apple of Contention between the Prince and the People: the <hi>King</hi> was accuſed of favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Popery, and deſigning to introduce it; and with it, <hi>Arbitrary Tyranny,</hi> the Natural Child of that <hi>Religion,</hi> becauſe he would not comply with the Zealous Fury of ſome Popular Spirits, to throw down the <hi>Hierarchy</hi> of the Church; which is one of the Fundamental Pillars of our Government. The other by their diſobedience to the known and Eſtabliſht Laws of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> became guilty of Diſloyalty, and were not without juſt cauſe ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected of Dangerous and Treaſonable Deſigns againſt the <hi>Royal</hi> Perſon and Government, which they did endeavour to conceal under the ſpecious pretences, and taking ſhews of <hi>Zeal</hi> againſt Popery, and eager forwardneſs to promote the pretended <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:51961:7"/>
            <p>Thus did theſe ſubtile Foxes, like <hi>Sampſons,</hi> while their Heads lookt ſeveral ways, carry thoſe Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands between their Tails, with which they ſet us all at laſt into a Flame; continually fanning with their peſtilent Breath, thoſe Jealouſies and mutual Animoſities, between the <hi>Soveraign</hi> and his <hi>Subjects,</hi> till they had reduced three of the moſt potent and flouriſhing Kingdoms in <hi>Europe</hi> into Aſhes, and had fill'd us with Blood and Confuſion. Thus far they had ſucceeded in their <hi>Enterpriſe,</hi> that they had ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely ruin'd the <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and pull'd down the old <hi>Cathedral,</hi> without Eſtabliſhing, or ſo much as ever intending, ſo far as any body could conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, any <hi>Church</hi> at all; and while in Policy they tolerated all <hi>Religions,</hi> they fairly opened a way for us to have none at all; and which was the thing the <hi>Jeſuites</hi> aimed at, to work us from our own Diviſions to deſtroy one another, and at laſt, either by Force or Policy, to reduce us to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church:</hi> And doubtleſs they were in hopes in a little time to have accompliſhed this great <hi>Deſign;</hi> when unexpected Providence, what by the Peoples general wearineſs of the <hi>Tyranny</hi> of thoſe many Governments, and by the <hi>Loyalty</hi> of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> whom no Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty nor Oppreſſion could remove from their firm Principles of <hi>Allegiance;</hi> brought back with the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Joy</hi> of the People, their long <hi>Deſire,</hi> our Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed <hi>Soveraign,</hi> Reſtoring Him miraculouſly to a Peaceful <hi>Throne;</hi> and with Him, Reſtoring to theſe Languiſhing <hi>Nations</hi> their Antient Government and Laws, their long-wanted Liberty, and <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:51961:8"/>
            <p>Now were the <hi>Roman Conſpirators</hi> at a loſs again, ſeeing their hopes defeated, and their expectations gone; and therefore encouraged by former Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes and Experience, they begun to play their old Leſſons over again; and we had ſcarcely taken breath after our violent <hi>Revolutions,</hi> when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan again to trouble our calm <hi>Waters,</hi> that ſo they might fiſh with more advantage: But by the <hi>Loy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lty</hi> of the Parliament, and Vigilance of the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> that being like to prove a Work of too long time for Men of ſo much impatience; and though they had made ſo great a progreſs as to raiſe ſome Diſorders in <hi>Scotland,</hi> for which two of them were under the diſguiſe of Presbyterians executed there; yet the generality of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were too ſenſible of the goodneſs of their preſent <hi>Condition,</hi> and ſufficiently inſtructed in the <hi>Calamities</hi> of a late <hi>Civil War,</hi> to enter into a ſecond; and above all, this great <hi>City</hi> manifeſting upon all occaſions great Teſtimonies of their <hi>Loyalty</hi> and Fidelity to His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> and the Government, they were forced upon new<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and more precipitate <hi>Counſels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How they have managed their <hi>Affairs,</hi> and with what cruelty they had laid their Deſigns, is by the Goodneſs of God already in a great meaſure, and it is to be hoped will be fully diſcovered; it was in ſhort a Deſign againſt His <hi>Majesties</hi> Sacred Perſon, and the Government, our Laws, Lives, Liberties, and the Proteſtant Religion; a Deſign as univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſally laid, as it was to have been tragically execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: The preſent Race of our <hi>Kings,</hi> were either to have been wholly extirpated, or become vile
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51961:8"/>Tributaries to the <hi>Triple Mitre.</hi> One would think it impoſſible that ſuch barbarous and ſavage Actions ſhould proceed from any of <hi>Human Race;</hi> or that there would be found any, who have ſo far loſt the Native Generoſity of <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> which in the Times of the <hi>Papal Monarchy,</hi> durſt bid defiance to his Encroachments, as to proſtitute the <hi>Imperial Crown</hi> of theſe Realms to Vaſſallage and Slave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
            <p>A ſtolen ſmile will part from me, to think how all this while theſe Purblind <hi>Conſpirators</hi> could not ſee how ſhort an Enjoyment they, and their great Three Crown'd <hi>Maſter,</hi> muſt have had of the bloody Spoils of <hi>England.</hi> There is a certain great Neighbor of theirs, who has told a Pope, That he does not va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue his <note n="*" place="margin">Witneſs the Column erected at <hi>Rome</hi> in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of the <hi>Pope,</hi> for a Petty Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ont offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere.</note>
               <hi>Holineſs</hi> at a Farthing; and who would certainly have made the Moral of old <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s Fable good upon them; the <hi>Lion, Fox,</hi> and <hi>Bear,</hi> had made a Hunting Match; the <hi>Fox</hi> and <hi>Bear,</hi> Subtilty and Cruelty took the <hi>Prey;</hi> but the <hi>Lyon,</hi> as moſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful, challenged it wholly for himſelf, and had it without a Murmur from his fellow Hunters, who were glad at that rate to compound with his armed Paws, for the ſecurity of their own Skins.</p>
            <p>I canot believe, but that the whole <hi>World</hi> will entertain this diſcovery with <hi>Horror;</hi> and though the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> will with the greateſt <hi>Effrontery</hi> deny, or mitigate it, yet certainly their <hi>Religion</hi> will receive the Blow which they intended for ours: for who that is not reſolved to quit <hi>Hum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nity</hi> it ſelf, can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that <hi>Religion</hi> to be true, which is to be propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with Treaſons, Murders of the moſt <hi>Purple-dye,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:51961:9"/>violation of all that is Sacred in Human <hi>Society,</hi> Law, Juſtice, Equity, the moſt Solemn <hi>Oaths,</hi> Promiſes, and Covenants? Who can believe the Pope the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in Faith and Doctrine, when he ſhall under his moſt Authentique Hand and Seal, Abſolve the Subjects of any Prince from their Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Civil, and Religious <hi>Allegeance</hi> to their Lawful <hi>Soveraign;</hi> when he ſhall grant Pardons to whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall Murder him, and diſpence with all the <hi>Oaths</hi> that have been, or can be taken, to ſecure the <hi>Royal Perſon,</hi> or the Government by Law eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed? <hi>Nero</hi> that Monſter of <hi>Nature,</hi> from whom he claims a Succeſſion at leaſt of Practice, ſet <hi>Rome</hi> on fire, ſlew his Friends, made Cruelty his diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement, and became a <hi>Parricide</hi> out of Curioſity, Ripping up his Mothers Belly, that he might ſee the Neſt that had brought that <hi>Viper</hi> into the <hi>World.</hi> Flaming <hi>London</hi> is a witneſs that the ſecond <hi>Rome</hi> can equal, if not exceed the Firſt; and the Pope ſcorns to come behind <hi>Nero,</hi> ſince he can Command, Authorize, and Pardon the Murder of thoſe who are the common Parents of our Country; and more than that, who wear the Sacred <hi>Character</hi> of the <hi>Eternal Majeſty,</hi> being <hi>Gods</hi> to Men, though but Men to <hi>GOD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How <hi>God Almighty</hi> does and will reſent this Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front and Indignity put upon him by this Uſupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> is in ſome meaſure vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible already; and 'tis to be hoped, will yet be more, to the Shame and Confuſion of ſuch pretended <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion,</hi> but real <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> and moſt Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical <hi>Impiety;</hi> and how far the reſt of the Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51961:9"/>Heads of <hi>Europe,</hi> will by this example become ſenſible of their own danger, and the common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury herein offered to all the <hi>Royal Masters</hi> of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> I cannot tell, but <hi>Cum proximus Ardet <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legon;</hi> When their Neighbors Houſe is threatned to be fired over his Head, it is time for them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o look about them: No Prince can live in ſecurity, ſo long as there is Poiſon, Piſtol, or Ponyard in the hands of ſuch Deſperadoes, as not valuing their own are, for the Intereſt of the <hi>Catholick Religion,</hi> Maſters of other Mens Lives; ſo long as the Pope may for <hi>Hereſie</hi> Arraign, Condemn, Excommunicate, Depoſe, and Deprive Soveraign <hi>Kings</hi> in the <hi>Conſiſtory,</hi> and Arm both their own, and the Subjects of Foreign <hi>Nations</hi> againſt them; gives his Benediction, with Rewards and Promiſes both of Heaven and Earth, to take away the lives of the <hi>Heirs,</hi> that ſo he may ſeize upon the Inheritance; and ſo long as he chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenges to himſelf the boundleſs <hi>Prerogative</hi> of being the Sole and <hi>Supreme Judge</hi> of what is <hi>Hereſie,</hi> and by virtue of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ower, may define whatſoever is contrary to his Grandeur and <hi>Intereſt,</hi> to be that damnable and <hi>Capital Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this is not our Concern, our Neighbors may do as they ſhall pleaſe themſelves, and Nurſe this <hi>Mitre</hi> till it ſhall devour the <hi>Crown;</hi> we have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing nearer home to employ our thoughts, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, and moſt induſtrious endeavors upon; and with that <hi>Charity</hi> which begins at home, to take care how we may ſecure our ſelves.</p>
            <p>That all Degrees, Ranks and Conditions of Men, are poſſeſſed with a real deteſtation and abhorrence
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51961:10"/>of ſuch a villanous deſign, there can be no reaſon to make a doubt; their own <hi>Interest</hi> will oblige them to it; had the Net of this great <hi>Roman Fiſher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> been drawn up upon us, all had been Fiſh that had come to the Net, all would have been involved in the common Calamity; for had the <hi>Miſchief</hi> been formed into perfect <hi>Monſter,</hi> had it come to its growth and ſtrength, all Sorts and Degrees of Men, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out difference or diſtinction, who would not have abandoned the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and ſubmitted to the <hi>Roman Yoak,</hi> muſt have fallen as Sacrifices if not to their Religion, yet to that Policy which neceſſarily attends Cruelty and Uſurpation, the <hi>Deities</hi> which now the <hi>Romans</hi> worſhip. Nor could theſe ambitious <hi>Zealots,</hi> have ever believed their unjuſt Dominion ſufficiently ſecured from the danger of future <hi>Relapſes,</hi> but by the intire deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all thoſe, whom they could not truſt, or might either ſuſpect or fear, &amp; by ſeizing their Eſtates, to enable themſelves with Force and <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and <hi>Tyranny</hi> to take away the Liberties and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of oppoſing them, from ſuch as they muſt permit to ſurvive the general <hi>Maſſacre;</hi> that ſo they might be out of fear from thoſe whom they intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make, and treat like <hi>Slaves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had the <hi>Royal Oak</hi> fallen under their treacherous deſigns, what favour or mercy, could either the lofty <hi>Cedars,</hi> or the humble Shrubs and Plebeians of the Wood have expected from their hands? They who were grown ſo hardned in Miſchief, to attempt firſt upon the <hi>Scepter,</hi> would never in their <hi>Conſciences</hi> have ſcrupled at the <hi>Sheephook:</hi> They
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51961:10"/>who could not bluſh to ſhed the Blood of the <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign,</hi> would never have diſputed to let out whole Rivers of the Subjects.</p>
            <p>If this had been the <hi>Project</hi> of a few <hi>Zealous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſes,</hi> or managed by the hot Brains of ſome <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Heads;</hi> or had it been the undertaking of ſome few Diſcontented <hi>Laicks,</hi> there might have been ſome colour of excuſe for the <hi>Religion</hi> in general, there being ill Men of all <hi>Religions,</hi> and even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong thoſe who profeſs the Trueſt: When there were but Twelve <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> one of them was a <hi>Devil,</hi> a <hi>Traitor,</hi> and covetous <hi>Murderer:</hi> But when <hi>He,</hi> who ſtiles himſelf the <hi>Vicar</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> the Succeſſor of <hi>St. Peter</hi> and <hi>St. Paul,</hi> the Infallible <hi>Head</hi> of the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church,</hi> who cannot <hi>Err</hi> from the <hi>True Faith,</hi> the <hi>Supreme Judge</hi> of Controverſies, the <hi>Keeper</hi> of the <hi>Keyes</hi> of Heaven and Earth, Hell and Purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, when he ſhall be the Principal <hi>Inſtigator,</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moter and Encourager of <hi>Murder, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurpation, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> ſure no Man can believe, but that either the Faith of <hi>Rome</hi> is not the <hi>Catholique</hi> Faith, or that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> if this be her <hi>Faith,</hi> is no true part of the <hi>Catholique Church.</hi> For if we may <hi>Judge</hi> of the Tree by the Fruits, ſuch horrid and infamous Practices, ſeem to make the <hi>Pope</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, the Succeſſor of <hi>Iſcariot,</hi> who betray'd his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> to be Crucified, rather then of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who was himſelf Crucified for Planting and Propagating the Faith of <hi>Chriſt</hi> by Rules of Meekneſs, Tenderneſs, Love to all Men, and particular obedience to Kings as <hi>Supreme,</hi> and to <hi>Magistrates</hi> as Gods Vicegerents and Miniſters of Juſtice upon <hi>Earth;</hi> and indeed,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51961:11"/>whoever ſhall conſider theſe Actions of the <hi>Pope</hi> and the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> will think them to be expected only from the fierce <hi>Cannibals</hi> of the <hi>Weſt Indies,</hi> who have neither Morality, Law, nor Religion; and not from thoſe who ſtile themſelves the <hi>Pillar and Ground of Truth,</hi> the only Profeſſors of the true Faith and <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is certainly therefore the intereſt of every Man who is not a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and I doubt not the wiſhes and deſires of all Men, to be ſecured from the attempts of ſuch inhumane and cruel Men, who would make no more difficulty to cut the Throat of a <hi>Heretique Proteſtant,</hi> than to daſh out the Brains of a <hi>Mad Dog;</hi> and above all the reſt of <hi>England,</hi> it is the more particular concern of this great and populous <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London</hi> to be ſecured from them: Her-pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Glory</hi> may be a ſad Teſtimony of their infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Treachery, and helliſh <hi>Malice;</hi> Her <hi>Beauty</hi> is raiſed upon thoſe Aſhes to which they had reduced her, one of them confeſſed and died for it; and in which we have reaſon to think they deſigned to bury her for ever: the damp, that he put upon her in her preſent <hi>Trade,</hi> which is deſervedly the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral complaint, is from their <hi>Practices;</hi> and that inſecurity in which we live to fall into the hands of theſe mercileſs <hi>Aſſaſſinates,</hi> makes Mens lives un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſie, their dayes unquiet, and their nights tedious, and both expenſive, beyond the proportion of their preſent Trade, whil'ſt they are obliged by ſuch ſtrong and conſtant <hi>Guards,</hi> to purchaſe their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity at the expence of their <hi>Mony,</hi> Time and Health.</p>
            <p>That His Moſt <hi>Sacred Majeſty,</hi> and the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51961:11"/>Houſes of <hi>Parliament</hi> are Aſſiduous and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, both to diſcover and puniſh the <hi>Authors</hi> of theſe <hi>Treaſons</hi> and Miſchiefs, is obvious to all Men; that they will take all the care that mortal Men can do, both to ſecure us for the preſent, and eſtabliſh us for the future upon the beſt Foundations of a laſting <hi>Safety,</hi> no perſon can doubt: But when they have done their part to the utmoſt; when they have wound up their <hi>Juſtice</hi> and their <hi>Counſels</hi> to the higheſt pitch of <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> when they have made the <hi>Fence</hi> of the Laws impregnable in all appearance; yet unleſs every <hi>Subject</hi> in his Place, will contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute ſomething towards the common <hi>Security,</hi> theſe pernicious Foxes will either lurk undiſcover'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, or creep through and eſcape the hands of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> though it purſue them never ſo cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
            <p>For if we can ſuppoſe the ſtrongeſt Bonds of <hi>Oaths of Allegeance, Supremacy, Tests, Abrenunciati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Declarations,</hi> or what Human Wiſdom can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe; let the words be as plain and perſpicuous as the Beams of <hi>Day;</hi> let all the care imaginable be taken to obviate them in their <hi>Equivocations, Mental Reſervations</hi> and <hi>Evaſions;</hi> let them declare that they believe that the <hi>Pope</hi> has no Power to Abſolve them; or that ſuch <hi>Oaths</hi> are not null and void from the beginning, becauſe there was not <hi>Bona fides ab initio:</hi> All this will not be ſufficient; for the moſt <hi>Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> among the <hi>Papiſts</hi> will be the leaſt ſcrupulous of any <hi>Oath</hi> that ſhall be tendred to them; nor will think this <hi>Perjury,</hi> or if it be, will they therefore decline it, ſo long as they are before-hand armed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51961:12"/>with an <hi>Antidote</hi> from <hi>Rome,</hi> which can expel all the Poiſon and the danger of ſuch <hi>Oaths,</hi> and not only ſo, but render them meritorious, as being part of the Perſecution which they ſuffer from <hi>Heretiques,</hi> in defence of the <hi>Catholique Religion;</hi> and they who fear the <hi>Pope</hi> more than <hi>God,</hi> and believe that he has power to remit all Sins of this <hi>Nature,</hi> if they eſteem them Sins, will think themſelves ſecure from the ſtroak of <hi>Divine Vengeance</hi> due to perjured Heads; and which is all they have to look too, they imagine themſelves hereby ſure to eſcape the danger and ſeverity of <hi>Human Laws.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus eluding the Tryal and Diſcrimination of an <hi>Oath,</hi> they will ſecurely enjoy their Lives and Liberties, and remain <hi>Maſters</hi> of all the Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of ſtill contriving, and managing their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievous <hi>Counſels,</hi> and Treaſonable <hi>Attempts:</hi> For this we are to aſſure our ſelves, that ſo long as they can eſcape the danger of puniſhment, they will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver give over the Enterpriſe. And though <hi>God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty</hi> may not permit them to run to the full ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of their <hi>Malice,</hi> which terminates in nothing ſhort of our utter <hi>Ruine,</hi> the Subverſion of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and Extirpation of the very Name and <hi>Religion</hi> of the Proteſtants; yet will they give us many Diſturbances as to our Peace and Quiet, and be able to do us many private Miſchiefs, both at home and abroad: for they are a Generation of Men too learnedly <hi>malicious,</hi> and too well acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Italian Genius</hi> of <hi>Matchiavel,</hi> and <hi>Caeſar Borgia,</hi> not to be able to do us all poſſible Injuries; and they are too inveterate not to be feared at all
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51961:12"/>times; but more eſpecially when they either <hi>flatter</hi> us, or ſeem aſleep, and not to regard us. <hi>Manet altâ mente repoſtum;</hi> The hatred and animoſity which they bear us, is ſucceſſive and <hi>eternal;</hi> the Quarrel is <hi>Immortal,</hi> and made an <hi>Intail</hi> like that of <hi>Hannibals</hi> againſt <hi>Rome;</hi> the old rigid <hi>Carthagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> his Father ſwore him before the <hi>Altars</hi> of his Country Gods, that he ſhould be <hi>perpetuus Romani nominis Oſor,</hi> and to eſpouſe an <hi>Eternal</hi> hatred of the very <hi>Roman Name;</hi> nor need we much doubt but they have taken the ſame <hi>Oath</hi> before their <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars,</hi> to hate the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> Not all the Clemency, Indulgence, or Humanity that can be ſhewn them, is capable of taming this bequeathed <hi>Fierceneſs</hi> againſt us; and let poor <hi>Proteſtants</hi> treat them with all the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> meekneſs, temper, and compaſſion, as becomes the noble profeſſion of their innocent and Heavenly <hi>Religion;</hi> they will upon the firſt opportunity, repay them with the blackeſt ingratitude, and moſt incompaſſionate <hi>Cruelty;</hi> two Crimes, which cannot be outdone by all the Vices of <hi>Nature</hi> and of <hi>Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That theſe men have been the great <hi>Maſters</hi> who have improved all our <hi>Diſſentions,</hi> few judicious and obſerving <hi>People</hi> have for many years doubted, and it is now apparent from the Voluntary Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of thoſe who have had ſufficient Reaſon to know <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Oats</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bedow.</hi>
               </note> and whoever Conſiders how much it was their <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> to daſh us one againſt another and ſo to break us in pieces, and what large advantages they have made of our mutual <hi>diſcords;</hi> to what Extremities by this ſingle <hi>Artifice</hi> they had reduced us; while
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51961:13"/>with our own Swords, we did all we could, and almoſt all they could deſire of us to undo our ſelves, and ruine both the <hi>Reputation</hi> and <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant</hi> Cauſe it ſelf; I ſay, whoever will bring theſe things together, will be eaſily induced to believe, that they have been the prime <hi>Actors</hi> in, as well as contrivers of our <hi>Diviſions.</hi> Thus did we give them opportunity to enter among us with ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and while, as the late dying <hi>Archbiſhop Laud</hi> in his Speech upon the <hi>Scaffold</hi> prophetically ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, the Cry of <hi>Veniunt Romani</hi> the <hi>Romans</hi> are coming in upon us, went among a Credulous and abuſed <hi>People,</hi> theſe very <hi>Romans</hi> whom we ſo much feared, under other names came in reality upon us, and had almoſt taken away our Place, &amp;c. <hi>Nation.</hi> Thus did we furniſh them with Conveniency and Arguments to gain <hi>Proſelytes</hi> to their boaſted <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> while they in return, furniſht us with mutual Animoſities, Jealouſies, and <hi>Arms</hi> to deſtroy our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Nor is this the onely fruit which they have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready reaped, and do hope ſtill to reap from thoſe Seeds of <hi>Diſcord</hi> which they have ſown, and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtriouſly cultivated among us: Here likewiſe they poſt themſelves as in a <hi>wood,</hi> and lie in <hi>Ambuſcade,</hi> ready to annoy us; and in the mean time remain ſecure from being attaqued themſelves, or ſo much as known or diſcovered; and being able to trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form themſelves into any ſhape, like Highwaymen who have committed <hi>Murder</hi> and <hi>Robbery,</hi> 'tis but turning the Coat and changing the <hi>Peruque,</hi> and they face and laugh at the <hi>Hue and Cry</hi> which does purſue them.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51961:13"/>
            <p>How dangerous their Company is in this <hi>Town,</hi> ſeveral tragical <hi>Examples</hi> have lately convinced us; nor can we be ſecure from Fire, Sword, and Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ſo long as theſe Mortal <hi>Enemies</hi> Lodge within us. Now it is morally impoſſible, and they know it, and for that very purpoſe have been ſo very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious to promote our <hi>diviſions,</hi> I ſay it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible ſo long as thoſe continue, either to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, or get quit of them; ſince when they find themſelves cloſely hunted by the Laws, they will undoubtedly <hi>Herd</hi> with ſome <hi>Sect</hi> or other and ſo Eſcape.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Majeſty</hi> by his <hi>Proclamation</hi> has commanded all <hi>Papists</hi> who are not Houſeholders, Travellers, &amp;c. to depart from this his <hi>Imperial City:</hi> but who believes that there are not great numbers of them, and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Prieſts</hi> eſpecially ſtill in <hi>Town?</hi> and in probability, thoſe who are moſt guilty, and moſt deſperate: for here in the Crowd they think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves ſecure, which they could not hope to be in the <hi>Country,</hi> where the <hi>Jealous peaſants,</hi> not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with any but their fellow <hi>Cottagers,</hi> are all in an uproar at the ſight of a ſtrange face, and read Firebals and <hi>Treaſon</hi> in his very <hi>Countenance;</hi> and therefore will not fail to carry him before his <hi>Worſhip</hi> the next <hi>Juſtice</hi> of the <hi>Peace;</hi> and the <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice</hi> for his own ſecurity is bound to ſecure ſuch perſons as appear ſuſpitious, unleſs they can give a very good account ot themſelves. Whereas here in Town, a <hi>Prieſt</hi> or <hi>Jeſuit</hi> takes a Lodging at a <hi>Quakers,</hi> can <hi>thou</hi> and <hi>thee,</hi> and <hi>yea</hi> and <hi>nay,</hi> as well as the beſt of them; goes to the <hi>Silent meeting</hi> with
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51961:14"/>his <hi>Landlord,</hi> and it may be upon occaſion, if the <hi>Spirit moves,</hi> he can diſgorge himſelf againſt the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> the Hirelings; the burden of <hi>Tithes,</hi> the uſeleſneſs of <hi>humane Learning,</hi> he can talk of the <hi>light</hi> within him, and the witneſs of God, and vili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the <hi>Scriptures</hi> as a dead and carnal Letter; and ſuch <hi>Common-places</hi> of diſcourſe as are grateful to the People; and ſo he paſſes for one of their <hi>Friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Jeſuit incognito</hi> paſſing thus under the Maſque of a <hi>Sectary,</hi> the <hi>Conſtables</hi> of the <hi>Pariſh,</hi> as is their duty, and purſuant to the publick <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> for the <hi>Common ſecurity,</hi> come to my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour the <hi>Quakers</hi> to know what <hi>Lodgers</hi> he has in his houſe; he ſtraight informs them ſuch a perſon, and gives in the falſe name by which he goes; they inquire what he is? he tells them he is one of their Friends who has lodged there ſo long; the Officers it may be only in <hi>drollery</hi> tell him they ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect he is a <hi>Prieſt</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church;</hi> Nay verily that he is ſure he is not, for he hates the <hi>Beaſt</hi> and the <hi>Scarlet Whore,</hi> he has heard him ſay ſo, in the Meeting. Well! the <hi>Lodger</hi> himſelf, it may be if within, is ſo confident as to face the <hi>Officers,</hi> who tell him he muſt take the <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Obedience;</hi> Nay, replies he, <hi>Friends,</hi> I cannot ſwear, the light with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in me witneſſes to the truth, which ſays, <hi>Swear not at all,</hi> but let your <hi>Yea be Yea, and Nay Nay,</hi> and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins an <hi>Harangue</hi> againſt all <hi>Oaths.</hi> The <hi>Officers</hi> impoſed upon as well as the Good man of the Houſe, by the fineneſs of the <hi>ſtratagem,</hi> leave him, onely entring his borrowed name in the Liſt, without
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51961:14"/>ſuſpition that he is a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and much leſs, a <hi>Prieſt or Jeſuit.</hi> Thus does he ſcape <hi>Scot-free,</hi> and is at liberty; and when in a place remote from his <hi>quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> he <hi>rendezvouzes</hi> with his fellow adventurers in <hi>Maſquerade,</hi> they laugh at all the <hi>World;</hi> and in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight of all <hi>Laws</hi> and the ſtricteſt ſearch, as if they had King <hi>Gyges</hi> his enchanted Ring, they walk in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible and ſecure; and want neither freedom, nor opportunity, to contrive, carry on, and execute their horrible deſigns, of firing our <hi>City;</hi> aſſaſſina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch as are active in oppoſing them; endanger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as much as ever the <hi>Royal Perſon,</hi> the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and <hi>Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not particularize in this <hi>Sect,</hi> as the onely ſhelter or ſecure harbor for theſe <hi>Popiſh Conſpirators,</hi> though it may be, their eſteeming all <hi>Oaths</hi> unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, their deriding and diſuſing the holy <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> their Contempt of the <hi>Scripture,</hi> their ſtate of perfection in this life, and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their <hi>Tenets,</hi> ſo agreable to the <hi>Romiſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines</hi> and deſigns, qualifie them more then many others to be deceived by the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and are more proper to afford them ſhelter and ſecurity.</p>
            <p>Not that this will excuſe any other Sects from the ſame danger; and I ſee no reaſon why we ſhould not ſuſpect, that ſeveral ſtickling <hi>Itinerant Teachers,</hi> who travel as <hi>Apostles</hi> among the <hi>Independents, Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, &amp;c.</hi> may not as well be <hi>Jeſuits</hi> under theſe diſguiſes, as thoſe two Executed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> who went under the Notion and <hi>Character</hi> of <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans;</hi> who yet, as Mr, <hi>Oats</hi> has depoſed, had their Commiſſions to Preach <hi>Sedition</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51961:15"/>the <hi>Rector</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Colledge</hi> of <hi>Jeſuits</hi> at <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> and he from the <hi>Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The is no queſtion but a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> can put on any dreſs of <hi>Religion,</hi> to ſerve the Intereſt of the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Cauſe,</hi> and will not ſcruple to take up the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage even of the <hi>good old Cauſe,</hi> and appear an eager <hi>Separatiſt</hi> in any ſhape, the better to accomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date himſelf with a Capacity of promoting our <hi>Ruine</hi> by our diſſentions and diviſions: this gives him a certain opportunity to unhinge people from their <hi>Allegiance</hi> to the <hi>Crown</hi> and Obedience to the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Order and Government of the <hi>Church,</hi> the two <hi>butts</hi> againſt which he levels all the arrows of his poiſoned <hi>quiver:</hi> and all the while he ſeems ſo fierce againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> and Ceremonies, he gains one point more of the <hi>Compaſs</hi> by which he <hi>ſails,</hi> which it is paſs undiſcovered, and under that diſguiſe to help to blow up the <hi>Coals</hi> of miſunderſtandings, Jealouſies, and Animoſities, between the <hi>King</hi> and his Subjects; with which at laſt he hopes to ſet them into a blaze, and to warm his own hands at the fire which ſhall conſume them.</p>
            <p>And to further this deſign, it is to be known that a <hi>Jeſuit</hi> can be of any quality, Trade or profeſſion, a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> a Merchant, a Lawyer, a Solicitor, a what you pleaſe: for the <hi>Romiſh Janizaries</hi> are the tribute Children of all <hi>Europe,</hi> of the moſt pregnant <hi>Genius</hi> and univerſal Capacity that can be gleaned up in any Schools; and theſe beſides their Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in which they are trained up ſuitably to their Inclinations, are alſo inſtructed in all ſuch arts, as may accompliſh them, and render them agreable in
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51961:15"/>converſation to all ſorts of people; and in order to their being ſerviceable to their Concealment. Who would have believed Mr <hi>Price,</hi> Steward to my Lord <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Worceſter</hi> to have been ſuch an eminent <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> as to merit the <hi>Character</hi> of one of the moſt ingenious and wiſeſt men in orders in the <hi>World?</hi> in all companies he paſſed for an ingenious man and a <hi>Virtuoſo,</hi> and I have heard a worthy Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman and famous <hi>Lawyer</hi> ſay, he thought he was one of the ableſt <hi>Solicitors</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> but he, as well as others were, I dare be confident far from ſuſpecting him to be what he is now charged with, or the wiſe man upon whom the <hi>Conſpirators</hi> ſo much relied for his Counſels and <hi>Conduct</hi> of their late <hi>Helliſh Conjuration?</hi> and in ſuch a crowd of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of all ſorts as inhabit this Spatious <hi>City,</hi> and over grown <hi>Suburbs,</hi> how eaſie a thing is it for great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of them to ſettle themſelves as Inhabitants, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the <hi>ſecular Jeſuits,</hi> who apply themſelves to <hi>Civil</hi> affairs, as <hi>Factors</hi> and <hi>Merchants</hi> Trading to Foreign parts? and how impoſſible is it to diſcover them to be what they are, deteſtable <hi>Conſpirators</hi> who maintain a ſecret Correſpondence with all <hi>Courts</hi> of the <hi>Roman Religion</hi> to our prejudice, and principally with the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſo long as they publickly own themſelves to be of ſome <hi>ſect</hi> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and paſs under the Characters of <hi>Presbyterians, Independants, Anabaptiſts,</hi> or any thing but of the <hi>Church of England:</hi> for that is their mortal hatred; that, is what they do above all things covet to deſtroy; as being the <hi>frontier</hi> and <hi>Bastion</hi> of the <hi>Protestant Religion:</hi> and could they intirely ruine
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51961:16"/>that, which is the thing they labor for night and day, with all the application imaginable, <hi>velis &amp; remis,</hi> tooth and nail, and for the accompliſhment of which great work they transform themſelves into ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure theſe various diſguiſes, they make themſelves ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure of the Reſt; whom they would play at one another, till they worried and devour themſelves; and at laſt, fall an eaſie Conqueſt to the <hi>Roman Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whoever he was that writ that diſcovery made to the late <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Archbiſhop Land,</hi> he aſſures us that of the four Orders, of Eccleſiaſticks, Politicks, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, and Intelligencers, ſcarcely all <hi>Italy, Spain,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> afforded ſo great a number of <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> as the City of <hi>London</hi> then did, and that there were more than fifty <hi>Scottiſh Jeſuits</hi> then, who had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired againſt the King and Government, by raiſing a <hi>Civil War</hi> among us: and we have no reaſon to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that their numbers are leſſened, when their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies are increaſed. Under theſe diſguiſes they do more effectually carry on their wicked deſigns of keeping up and increaſing our diſorders and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions; for it is the cloſe <hi>Cabal</hi> that does the miſchief; and poiſons the Common people of any Sect with <hi>principles</hi> of diſloyalty and faction; when they are <hi>under the Roſe</hi> then do they vomit out all they can to enrage people againſt the Government both in <hi>Church and Stale:</hi> whereas the publick diſcourſes of moſt <hi>diſſenters,</hi> either out of Ingenuity or fear of puniſhment, are managed with more <hi>Caution,</hi> and leſs <hi>violence.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:51961:16"/>
            <p>I am not ſo vain as to believe, that theſe <hi>Truths</hi> or at leaſt dangerous probabilities ſhould gain in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire <hi>Credit</hi> even with thoſe whom they do ſo near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concern; I am but too ſenſible that the impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which ſome men have received into their minds, are ſo firmly rivetted into their <hi>belief,</hi> that they will not be perſwaded to abandon them, though that be they only probable way to eſtabliſh their own, and the Common ſafety and ſecurity of our <hi>Nation,</hi> one may almoſt with the ſame eaſe remove <hi>Black-heath,</hi> as perſwade ſome people that they are ſecretly man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aged by <hi>Romiſh Prieſts and Jeſuits;</hi> that they are acceſſory to the dangers of introducing <hi>Popery;</hi> or that they ſecure them from diſcovery, and that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment which in the opinion of all men they have juſtly merited.</p>
            <p>But certainly they who wiſh well to their <hi>Native Country;</hi> to the publick peace and ſecurity of the <hi>Nation;</hi> to their own lives, Liberty, Property, or <hi>Poſterity;</hi> if they will act according to the natural principle of ſelf-preſervation, or the <hi>Dictates</hi> either of Law, Reaſon, or Religion, muſt do it theſe two ways.</p>
            <p>Either firſt, they muſt contribute all they can actively, towards the diſcovery of theſe dangerous <hi>Conſpirators;</hi> by all lawful ways and means.</p>
            <p>Or ſecondly, if that comes not within their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er or knowledge to effect, they muſt do all they can not to obſtruct their diſcovery, or be acceſſory to their Concealment; and they ought with the ſame <hi>Caution</hi> to avoid the ſheltring, or even unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſecuring of them from the hands of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> as
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51961:17"/>they would avoid the Common miſchiefs, dangers, and <hi>Calamities,</hi> which they and the whole <hi>Nation,</hi> may fear from them, or ſuffer for want of ſuch a diſcovery.</p>
            <p>Now how willing ſoever any people may be to purſue at once their <hi>duty</hi> and great <hi>Interest,</hi> by the firſt, yet in regard it will be difficult, hazzardous, and uncertain how they ſhall ſucceed; and the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious cunning and diſſimulation of theſe <hi>Malefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> protecting them, not only from <hi>vulgar</hi> diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but many times from the moſt <hi>Cri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ical,</hi> and piercing Eyes of the wiſeſt <hi>Stateſmen;</hi> there can therefore be nothing left for all true and honeſt <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> and real <hi>Protestants,</hi> but to clear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and by ſuch a <hi>Touchſtone</hi> as will certainly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh, the <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Jeſuit</hi> from the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> to vindicate themſelves and diſcover the other.</p>
            <p>It may be ſome perſons will think me very Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſident in offering ſuch a <hi>Shibboleth</hi> as may certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly detect theſe <hi>Ephraimites,</hi> if all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> would make uſe of it: but I am not ſollicitous what any perſons may think: if it be ſuch an eaſie <hi>Expedient</hi> as will do the work, ſo effectually, that the <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> of our Peace, <hi>Religion,</hi> and Country, cannot avoid being diſcovered by it; and if it be ſuch a <hi>Method</hi> as all true <hi>Proteſtants</hi> may and ought to make uſe of; it will be the opinion of the beſt and wiſeſt men, and that is only valuable, that they who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe ſuch a <hi>Teſt</hi> and way of Trial, muſt, either be Accomplices and <hi>Confederates</hi> with <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits;</hi> or however acceſſory to all the <hi>Miſchiefs</hi> which may happen, by their obſtructing and fruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating ſuch a <hi>Diſcovery.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:51961:17"/>
            <p>It has before been intimated, and is notoriouſly obſervable by all people, how they do, and may elude all <hi>Oaths</hi> which may be offer'd them as a way of diſcrimination; for the greateſt <hi>Criminals,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the greateſt concern to lie conceal'd, will not ſcruple in their extreme danger and neceſſity, any or all the <hi>Oaths</hi> that can be framed or offer'd them to take: and being before hand arm'd by diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations and <hi>pardons</hi> from their <hi>Omnipotent Pope,</hi> they will conſult their own ſafety and the good of the <hi>Catholick Cauſe,</hi> without fear of ſwearing, or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwearing themſelves; ſo that ſuch <hi>Oaths</hi> will prove but <hi>Cobwebs</hi> to take the leſſer Flies; while the <hi>Waſps</hi> and <hi>Hornets</hi> who carry the <hi>ſting</hi> and the <hi>poyſon</hi> will break through them and eſcape.</p>
            <p>Nay, poſſibly, they would not ſcruple to joyn with us in our <hi>Publick</hi> Service and Solemn <hi>Worſhip,</hi> which as much as ſome people account <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Superſtitious,</hi> the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do deteſt and abhor; Nor would they refuſe to hear Sermons in our <hi>Churches;</hi> though ſo long as there are ſo many <hi>Meetings</hi> of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral <hi>ſects</hi> they will be ſecured from thoſe hardſhips too: for it is but joyning themſelves to ſome of thoſe of the <hi>Separation,</hi> and they both avoid that way of <hi>Tryal,</hi> and are more able ſucceſsfully to proſecute their great deſign of overthrowing the Eſtabliſhed Government both <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that which they abhor, and eſteem ſo dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and deadly a <hi>ſin</hi> as cannot be capable of any <hi>Diſpenſation, Pardon,</hi> or <hi>Indulgence,</hi> is to <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate</hi> with <hi>Protestants,</hi> whom they believe and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:51961:18"/>the greateſt <hi>Hereticks,</hi> that ever were in the <hi>World;</hi> both in reſpect of their diſowning <hi>Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation,</hi> and becauſe we are all under the <hi>Popes</hi> Curſe and <hi>Cenſure</hi> of <hi>Excommunication.</hi> This is that which will in all probability diſtinguiſh the <hi>Papist</hi> and <hi>Jeſuit</hi> from the true <hi>Proteſtant;</hi> for whatever they may be allowed to do to ſecure themſelves in other particulars, they will never, ſo far as we yet know, be compelled by us, or allowed by their <hi>Superiors</hi> to partake with us in the <hi>Holy Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lords Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not ſpeak this to oppoſe any way of <hi>Publick</hi> proceedings againſt them by <hi>Oaths</hi> or <hi>Teſts</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their believing that there is no <hi>Tranſubstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation</hi> of the Elements of Bread and Wine at or afer the Conſecration of them in the Lords <hi>Supper, &amp;c.</hi> if their <hi>Conſciences</hi> can ſwallow and digeſt <hi>Perjury,</hi> much good may it do them; I am aſſured it can do us no injury, but will certainly render them obnoxious to that <hi>Vengeance</hi> which muſt and will infallibly fall upon perjur'd heads, and how ſudden or ſevere that will be, let them look to it, for it nearly concerns them, whatever they may think. What I offer, is only in a private way, and to private perſons, that they, in their <hi>ſphere</hi> may be aſſiſtant to the <hi>Publick Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Justice,</hi> and of <hi>State</hi> in the diſcovery of theſe dangerous and cunning ſort of Men; and thereby contributing what lies in our power, to our own particular and the general ſecurity of his <hi>Most Sacred Majeſty</hi> (whom God long preſerve!) the Government, our Lives, Liberties, Laws, properties, <hi>Religion,</hi> and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:51961:18"/>
               <hi>Posterity,</hi> from the outrages, violences, treaſons and <hi>Conſpiracies</hi> of theſe our inveterate and mortal <hi>Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And certainly would all people be perſwaded to be <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimous</hi> in this duty of coming three times at the leaſt in every Year to celebrate and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly receive the <hi>Holy Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per;</hi> and an account taken of all ſuch as refuſe and abſent themſelves; it would be impoſſible upon ſtrict enquiry into their manner of life and other Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and eſpecially tendering it to them on ſome <hi>Lords day</hi> next after ſuch their <hi>Examination,</hi> that they ſhould eſcape being diſcovered.</p>
            <p>One would think, that the propoſal, were ſo ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional ſo eaſie and ſo <hi>Religious,</hi> that none but the very <hi>Criminals</hi> themſelves, or their <hi>Acceſſories</hi> and <hi>Confederates</hi> ſhould refuſe this way of <hi>Tryal</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crimination; nor is it poſſible for any impartial per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to conſider and deliberate of it, but he muſt in his <hi>Judgment</hi> accuſe ſuch as ſhall refuſe it, as mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt favourers of <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits.</hi> The <hi>Law</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteems all ſuch as aid, conceal, and comfort <hi>Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> or protect them from diſcovery, to be <hi>Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors</hi> themſelves: and though they may plead for themſelves that they do not know them that are ſuch, and that may free them from the Penalties and danger of the <hi>Laws</hi> of Men; yet this <hi>Ignorance</hi> being perfectly voluntary, and proceeding from their wilful neglect of the way and means they had to detect them, it will not excuſe any perſons <hi>in foro Conſcientiae,</hi> before <hi>God</hi> and their own <hi>Conſciences,</hi> from being guilty, not only of the <hi>Murders</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51961:19"/>miſchiefs that have already happen'd, but of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever may or ſhall happen hereafter, for or by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their eſcaping undiſcovered: the true <hi>Maxim, qui non probibet cum po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, jubet,</hi> will infallibly lie againſt them at the great day of accounts: He who has a poſſibility of preventing a <hi>Miſchief,</hi> and either neglects or refuſes to do it, moſt certainly in the ſight of <hi>God</hi> the Righteous <hi>Judg,</hi> is guilty of it.</p>
            <p>I cannot tell what arguments to make choiſe of, in ſuch a Crowd of them as come thronging into my mind, to perſuade people to be willing and ready to perform a <hi>duty</hi> they owe to <hi>God</hi> and Man, in order to the ſecuring our <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> in their private Capacities, as well as the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is, to do all that can be done or deviſed in order to it: but however in ſhort I will offer theſe following, as to me appearing moſt preſſing and conſiderable: and if any other perſon can ſuggeſt more or more proper <hi>Motives</hi> it will become them, conſidering the preſent neceſſity, in charity to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and the <hi>Publick</hi> of offer them to the view and conſideration of the people of theſe <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt therefore I heartily wiſh that all people would conſider with themſelves, that what I offer is no <hi>Innovation;</hi> here is nothing propoſed to them or impoſed on them, but what the wiſdom of our <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> and of King <hi>James,</hi> eſteemed one of the wiſeſt <hi>Princes</hi> in the <hi>World,</hi> with the advice of his <hi>Parliament</hi> thought fit to paſs into a <hi>Law;</hi> and I hope that very <hi>Name</hi> will oblige people to believe the owe a <hi>duty</hi> of obedience to it: all the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51961:19"/>ſeems to be this, that when that <hi>Statute</hi> was made, all <hi>Protestants</hi> in general received the <hi>holy Sacrament,</hi> and onely the <hi>Papists</hi> were they who refuſed to do it; whereas now it is to be feared through the induſtry of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> among us, many who call themſelves <hi>Protestants</hi> will refuſe it as well as <hi>Papiſts:</hi> however to ſhew the duty and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of it, eſpecially were it a little accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dated to our preſent <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> and becauſe it does not lie in the way of every perſon to conſult the <hi>Statute</hi> at large, I will faithfully ſet down ſo much of it as concerns our preſent <hi>Caſe</hi> and purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Tertio Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobi cap. 4. An Act for the better diſcovering and repreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Popiſh Recuſants.</note>
               <hi>Foraſmuch as it is found by daily Experience that many his Majesties Subjects, that adhere in their hearts to the Popiſh Religion, by the Infection drawn from thence, and by the wicked and devilliſh counſel of Jeſuits, Seminaries, and other like perſons, dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to the Church and State, are ſo far perverted in the point of their loyalty and due Allegiance unto the Kings Majeſty, and the Crown of</hi> England, <hi>as they are ready to entertain and execute any treaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Conſpiracies and practiſes, as evidently appears by that more then barbarous and horrible attempt to have blown up with Gunpowder the King, Queen, Prince, Lords and Commons in the Houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment aſſembled, tending to the utter ſubverſion of the whole State, lately undertaken by the Inſtigation of Jeſuits and Seminaries, and in advancement of their Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by their Schollars taught and inſtructed by them to that purpoſe, which attempt by the only goodneſs of Almighty God was diſcovered and defeated: and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51961:20"/>whereas divers perſons</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Obſerve that they judged all ſuch as would not receive the Sacrament, to be Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</note>
               <hi>popiſhly affected do neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, to cover and hide their falſe hearts and with more ſufety to attend the opportunities to execute their miſchievous deſigns, repair ſometimes to Church, to avoid the Penalty of the Laws in that behalf provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the better diſcovery therefore of ſuch perſons, and their evil affections to the Kings Majeſty and the State of this Realm, to the end that being known their evil purpoſes may be better prevented, Be it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted by the Kings moſt excellent Majeſty, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal and the Commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament aſſembled, and by the authority of the ſame, That every popiſh Recuſant convicted or hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be convicted, which heretofore hath conformed him or her ſelf, or which ſhall hereafter conform him or her ſelf, and repair to the Church, and continue there during the time of Divine Service, according to the Laws and Statutes in that behalf made and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſhall within the firſt Year next after the end of this Seſſion of Parliament, or within the firſt year after that he or ſhe ſhall after this Seſſion of Parliament ſo conform him or her ſelf and repair to the Church as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, and after the firſt Year, once in every Year at the leaſt, receive the bleſſed Sacrament of the Lords Supper in the Church of that pariſh where he or ſhe ſhall moſt uſually abide, or be within the ſaid Year, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in by the true meaning of this Statue he or ſhe ought to receive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And if there be no ſuch pariſh Church, then in the Church next adjoyning to the place of his or her moſt uſual abode.</hi> The <hi>forfeiture</hi> for the firſt year <hi>twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:51961:20"/>pounds,</hi> for the ſecond Year <hi>forty pounds,</hi> and for every Year after <hi>threeſcore pounds.</hi> And the <hi>Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers</hi> are therein by rewards incouraged to preſent the Monthly abſence of all <hi>Recuſants</hi> from the <hi>Church;</hi> and for default of performing their <hi>duty</hi> are to be fined, as in the <hi>Statute</hi> more largly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears.</p>
            <p>Were this <hi>Statute</hi> with a little variation fitted for our <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> and duly put in <hi>Execution,</hi> it would be impoſſible but that all <hi>Recuſants</hi> muſt in a ſmall time be detected; and by conſequence thoſe dangerous <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Seminaries,</hi> whoſe whole deſign is to contrive, plot and execute, their horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Treaſons</hi> againſt both <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State:</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs people can be brought to comply with their own <hi>Intereſt</hi> as well as <hi>duty,</hi> the Excellent <hi>Method</hi> of that <hi>Law</hi> will be wholly impracticable; and it will be impoſſible to effect or attain the end, for which it was ſo wiſely intended: for ſo long as ſuch numbers of people who call themſelves <hi>Protestants,</hi> ſhall wilfully abſent themſelves from their Pariſh <hi>Churches,</hi> under the ſhew of <hi>Religion;</hi> and by their <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> ſo many who have no <hi>Religion</hi> at all, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly out of <hi>Idleneſs, looſeneſs</hi> and <hi>debauchery,</hi> ſhall ſtay at home, or do worſe abroad; theſe <hi>Traytors</hi> and <hi>Conſpirators</hi> will expect and find <hi>Security,</hi> by pretending to be <hi>diſſenters:</hi> and ſo long as there are ſo many who never regard any <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>God</hi> or Men, <hi>Civil</hi> or <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> which enjoyn them to receive the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> theſe will alſo paſs undiſcovered among the throng: for
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51961:21"/>it is all one to a <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> whether he paſs for a <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratist, Libertine,</hi> or <hi>Atheiſt,</hi> ſo long as he believes himſelf a good <hi>Catholique;</hi> and ſo long as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he has the opportunity of concealment, and thereby to proſecute the main <hi>Affair</hi> of propagating the <hi>Popiſh</hi> intereſt and <hi>Religion,</hi> by the Ruine of <hi>Protestants</hi> and <hi>Protestant Religion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore, in the ſecond place, I wiſh that all people would ſeriouſly reflect with themſelves at whoſe door the guilt will lie if by their means miſchief either publick or private overtake us? If the glorious <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> the <hi>Lamp</hi> of <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Truth</hi> ſhould come to be extinguiſhed by the Superſtitious darkneſs of <hi>Rome;</hi> if by the Subver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>England,</hi> the whole <hi>Protestant</hi> Cauſe ſhould ſuffer and be ruin'd, as in all probability, if that <hi>Bullwork</hi> were blown up, it muſt; or however ſuffer a <hi>perſecution</hi> as Sharp and cruel, as all thoſe <hi>ten</hi> of the <hi>Primitive ages</hi> put together; the <hi>Pagans</hi> being nothing ſo ingenious and wittily Cruel as the <hi>Jeſuits:</hi> if <hi>Millions</hi> of <hi>ſouls</hi> ſhould by a falſe <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> come to periſh <hi>Everlaſtingly:</hi> if our <hi>ſtreets</hi> and fields ſhould bluſh with the blood of <hi>Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Protestants,</hi> our houſes be reduced to aſhes, and our miſerable poſterity, with ſuch as ſhould ſurvive the Common <hi>Rage</hi> and deſolation, ſhould be made and ſold for bondſlaves: certainly there muſt be a ſtrict account given to <hi>Almighty God</hi> by whoſe default all this came to paſs? he gives us the means of ſecuring our ſelves and if we neglect, the fault and guilt will be wholly theirs who do obſtruct it; our blood will be upon their heads
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:51961:21"/>who hear the <hi>Trumpet</hi> and ſee the Sword coming and are ſo far from taking or giving the <hi>All-arm,</hi> that they joyn with ours and their own <hi>Enemies,</hi> if they be not ſecret <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and put a Sword into their hands to ſlay us: when <hi>God to whom vengeance belongs, ſhall make Inquiſition for blood he will not forget the cry of the poor;</hi> he will not forget thoſe who have been the occaſions, no more then thoſe who were the <hi>Actors</hi> of <hi>cruelty;</hi> and how it is poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for thoſe who obſtruct the diſcovery of <hi>Popiſh</hi> Prieſts and <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> not to be in the ſight of <hi>God</hi> and men guilty of all the Miſeries and miſchiefs which may be occaſioned by their concealment, I muſt proteſt my ſelf to be utterly ignorant.</p>
            <p>If there can be found any perſons ſo incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous as not to be apprehenſive of theſe dangers from them, and who may that way think to evade the neceſſity that lies upon them to contribute their utmoſt towards this <hi>Diſcovery:</hi> I will in ſhort endeavour to convince them from Former <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi> Let the horrible <hi>Maſsacre</hi> in <hi>France</hi> be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, in which according to the Relation even of Popiſh <hi>Historians,</hi> there periſhed near a hundred thouſand <hi>Proteſtants</hi> of all Ages, Sexes and Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: among which, twenty <hi>Lords</hi> of Eminency, twelve hundred <hi>Gentlemen,</hi> perſons of great Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition in the City of <hi>Paris,</hi> beſides what fell in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places: The ſubtile Contrivance and deep diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimulation with which it was managed, and the Exquiſite and ingenious <hi>Cruelty</hi> with which it was Executed, may ſufficiently Inſtruct us, what we are to truſt to, from ſuch <hi>Murderers,</hi> as glory in what
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:51961:22"/>is the ſhame and reproach of <hi>humane Nature,</hi> and render the moſt propitious and merciful <hi>Divinity,</hi> a cruel and ſanguinary <hi>Being,</hi> while they pretend to pleaſe and do him acceptable ſervice by ſuch bloody <hi>ſacrifices,</hi> as even <hi>heathens</hi> generally by the light of mere nature thought he abhorred: and who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage one another in miſchief, as if the <hi>Heavenly Paradice,</hi> were an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> and to be purchac'd with the price of blood: making ſuch actions of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orror and Cruelty as even exceed belief, merito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious performances capable to enrol them in the <hi>Catalogue</hi> of their <hi>Calender Saints:</hi> though we know none ſhall aſcend the <hi>holy Hill,</hi> but they who have clean hands as well as a pure heart.</p>
            <p>If this were not ſufficient to convince us at the expence of our <hi>neighbours,</hi> that which comes near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to us, is the Rebellion and <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Protestants</hi> in <hi>Ireland;</hi> the fatal <hi>Flambeau,</hi> which kindled our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Flames; the Cruelties which were then exerciſed are beyond Expreſſion and belief, three hundred thouſand ſouls periſhed by moſt, cruel deaths, according to computation, and <hi>God</hi> onely knows how many more, who could never be brought into account: and both in this and the <hi>Pariſian Maſsacre</hi> how many of thoſe who eſcaped the barbarous <hi>Rage</hi> of theſe mercileſs Butchers, periſhed afterwards with cold, hunger, nakedneſs, and all the hardſhips that attend the miſerable <hi>Condition</hi> to which they were expoſed? Whither to fly they knew not, but generally to the Woods and Forreſts, nor there, how to ſupply the neceſſities of <hi>Nature,</hi> having nothing left them
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:51961:22"/>but their lives, and no way of ſecuring thoſe long from the importunities of <hi>Cold</hi> and <hi>Famine;</hi> thus did they languiſh out a few miſerable hours till faint and weary, they became a prey to the <hi>Wolves,</hi> or fell into the paws of the <hi>Tories,</hi> the leſs merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful beaſts of the two. How many mournful and deſolate <hi>Widows,</hi> how many diſtreſſed and miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Orphans</hi> were then expoſed to all the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of lif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, before they knew what it was to live, and compelled to ſuffer all Extremities before they had done good or evil? Oh <hi>Injustice</hi> and uncomiſerating <hi>Cruelty!</hi> Oh more then brutiſh <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if the <hi>Romiſh Religion,</hi> command, encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and reward ſuch execrable barbarity, to be exerciſed upon the <hi>Innocent,</hi> what kind of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge</hi> can we imagine will they nor invent for thoſe, who dare oppoſe them? what torments, what lingring and retail deaths would they think e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for ſuch grand <hi>Heretiques</hi> as have ſlain their <hi>Apostles,</hi> whom they have employed to convert us to the <hi>Catholique</hi> Faith? <hi>Suetonius</hi> reports of <hi>Tiberius Caeſar,</hi> one of the <hi>Popes</hi> predeceſſors in the <hi>Roman</hi> throne, that he was a perſon ſo extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary cruel, that when a condemned perſon made it his importunate requeſt that he might be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patched quickly, he gave him this bitter <hi>Sarcaſm</hi> in anſwer, <hi>Nondum tecum redii in gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiam, No Sir, by your favour, you and I are not yet come to be ſuch good friends.</hi> Certainly not onely <hi>Romulus,</hi> but <hi>Rome</hi> her ſelf, her <hi>Kings, Emperors</hi> and <hi>Popes</hi> have been nurſed by <hi>Wolves;</hi> for ſure the breaſts
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:51961:23"/>of any thing that has humane ſhape, muſt inſtill ſentiments more tender and compaſſionate.</p>
            <p>There is not the moſt guilty head, that ſhall ſuffer deſerved <hi>Death</hi> for this Execrable <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> but will be eſteemed a Saint and <hi>Martyr</hi> in the <hi>Romiſh Church.</hi> Their great St. <hi>Thomas</hi> of <hi>Canter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury,</hi> ſo famous for his <hi>Shrine</hi> and <hi>Miracles,</hi> and the infamous <hi>Prayers</hi> made to him, as a <hi>Rival</hi> of the Son of <hi>God,</hi> who was by the account we have of Him in our Hiſtory, as ungrateful a Rebel to his <hi>Prince</hi> as can be imagined, may abundantly ſatisfie us in that particular: and if ever they come to reckon with us for ſuch precious blood; it may be eaſily conjectur'd, at what rate we muſt pay for thoſe <hi>Canonizations:</hi> let us be aſſured that a thouſand fold would not be look'd upon as a Compenſation for the lives of ſuch, as though we juſtly think <hi>Monsters,</hi> they believe to be <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> of men while they lived, and would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade their blind <hi>Votaries,</hi> that their very <hi>ſhrines</hi> can do<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Miracles</hi> after their Death. The <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Miniſters</hi> of <hi>Cruelty</hi> will never be ſo far reconciled to any <hi>Protestants</hi> that ſhall come with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in their power as to let them die at once; but would be as gratious to them as <hi>Caligula</hi> another Heathen <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Emperor</hi> was to ſuch as by his Tyranny were condemned to die; and that as the <hi>Historian</hi> relates was, that he was uſed to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them to be ſo executed <hi>ut ſe ſentirent mori.</hi> He would not have them loſe their lives by <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger de main</hi> and a ſlight of hand, but they muſt die by <hi>inches,</hi> and be ſenſible of every ſlow <hi>degree</hi> of approaching death.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:51961:23"/>
            <p>What pen can deſcribe the terrible dreſſes of uncommon deaths which would be invented for us? What tongue is able to expreſs its ghaſtly ſhapes, and the new faſhion'd garments of <hi>Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> or the rage of prevailing <hi>Popery?</hi> What heart can think of them, and of ſuffering them without the extremeſt <hi>horror?</hi> If death in his mildeſt and moſt natural appearance be ſo dreadful, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the title of <hi>the moſt terrible of all Terribles,</hi> what muſt he be when he is accompanied with all the Inventions of <hi>Tyranny?</hi> Who that ſaw them, or that heard the ſad <hi>Relation,</hi> can remember <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> in her raging Flames without aſtoniſhment? who can think upon her diſmal <hi>Ruines</hi> and aſhes without amazement? how did all faces gather blackneſs? how were they pained? what trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blings of heart at the flying <hi>Rumors</hi> of a <hi>Maſſacre</hi> then intended? What horror, Confuſion and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment would lay hold upon us, if we ſhould ſee our Enemies break in upon us like an over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing <hi>fire; a fire devouring before them, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them a flame burning, the land as the Garden of Eden before them, and behind them a deſolate wilderneſs?</hi> and no poſſibility of Eſcaping, but they who fled from the <hi>fire</hi> muſt fall upon the <hi>glittering Sword;</hi> they who eſcaped the drawn <hi>ſword;</hi> muſt periſh by <hi>Famine:</hi> and is it poſſible there ſhould be any perſons who will not contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute all they can to prevent theſe, which are not only imaginary, but real <hi>dangers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can it be look'd upon as a thing ſo indifferent, that people ſhould run all theſe <hi>hazzards,</hi> that a
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:51961:24"/>whole <hi>Nation</hi> ſhould lie at Stake and periſh, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they will abate a fooliſh <hi>ſcruple,</hi> or a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gid <hi>opinion</hi> to preſerve them; rather then go to the places dedicated to the ſervice of <hi>God</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the <hi>holy Sacrament,</hi> thereby to dec are their own <hi>Innocence,</hi> and detect the <hi>Authors</hi> of our dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, the Enemies of our Peace and Safety? Sure it is much eaſier to kneel at the <hi>holy Table,</hi> out of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence,</hi> not <hi>adoration,</hi> of the Bread and Wine; then to have the choice either to kneel and adore a <hi>Conſecrated Wafer,</hi> or to kneel at a Stake in <hi>Smithfield?</hi> Is it not far better to waſh our hands in innocence, and offer unto <hi>God</hi> the ſacrifice of thankſgiving; then to be guilty of the blood of ſo many as ſhould ſuffer by our being acceſſory to the accompliſhment of the Traiterous deſigns of the <hi>Jeſuits;</hi> and <hi>Sacrifice</hi> a <hi>Nation</hi> and many ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing generations, many people of other <hi>Nations</hi> to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> cruelty, meerly out of obſtinacy to our own prejudices, and it may be <hi>Fancies,</hi> which theſe very <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Seminaries</hi> have put in our heads? Certainly all thoſe who would not be thought, and in the Eye of the Law Eſteemed <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ought not to make the leaſt ſcruple to uſe this or any other lawful and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary expedient, that ſhall by the publick <hi>Wiſdom</hi> be thought neceſſary for our common preſervation: Nor will it be ſatisfactory that they ſhall in words diſown the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and declaim againſt it, or diſavow all <hi>Confederacy</hi> or <hi>Complotting</hi> with the <hi>Papists:</hi> the arranteſt <hi>Jeſuit</hi> in <hi>England</hi> will do this upon occaſion, to ſave his own life and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:51961:24"/>ours: and if they hinder the building up of the Walls of our <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> what does it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie how much they either ſay they do, or hate the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> ſince whether they conſpire with the <hi>Papists,</hi> or not, if they aſſiſt them in accompliſhing their intended <hi>Deſign</hi> of Ruining the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> it is the ſame thing? on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with this difference, that what the one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty does with <hi>Deſign,</hi> the other does with their <hi>folly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though men ſhould not value their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> Lives, or Liberties, which ſome people ſeem wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to part with, rather then aſſiſt the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> manifeſt their own innocency and detect the guilty, by endeavouring to promote the <hi>Common Security;</hi> yet one would think that which they call their <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Conſcience,</hi> ſhould oblige them to ſubmit to this or any other way of <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al</hi> and diſcrimination: they may hope for <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence</hi> from <hi>Protestants</hi> though of differing <hi>opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions,</hi> but they muſt not hope for the leaſt crums of <hi>Indulgence</hi> or favour from <hi>Papists;</hi> not all the ſervices they have done them will be remembred with the leaſt gratitude or tenderneſs; no conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of tender <hi>Conſciences</hi> is able to ſoften thoſe hearts who are more obdurate then <hi>Marble</hi> and <hi>Adamant,</hi> and as <hi>Charles</hi> the Ninth of <hi>France,</hi> in whoſe Reign the <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> was executed, ſaid to the Prince of <hi>Condé, Maſs, Death, or the Bastile,</hi> ſo would they ſay to all <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Diſſenters</hi> or others, <hi>Turn, or burn.</hi> For un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they be ſecret <hi>Papiſts,</hi> which no body can tell
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:51961:25"/>but they are, if they will not ſubmit to a way of Trial, and unleſs they reſolve to be open and profeſſed ones, upon the firſt opportunity; they cannot expect any favour or Clemency from pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing <hi>Popery;</hi> it is ſtream ſo <hi>rapid</hi> and <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,</hi> that it drowns all that will not ſwim down the <hi>furious torrent;</hi> and ſhould that inundation break our banks, all <hi>Proteſtants</hi> muſt either make Shipwrack of their Lives and <hi>Fortunes,</hi> or of their Faith and a good <hi>Conſcience,</hi> for they would ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie their rule to a letter, <hi>Extra Eccleſiam nulla ſalus,</hi> No ſafety in any ſence is with them to be found, expected, or ſo much as hoped for, out of the <hi>Ark</hi> of their <hi>Church.</hi> For though the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> as that which ſtands the main pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of <hi>Truth,</hi> be what they chiefly hate, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ruine; yet in the fall thereof they would certainly cruſh all other Pretenders to <hi>Reformation</hi> of what names or diſtinction ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
            <p>In extraordinary <hi>Caſes</hi> of ſuch impendent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, people do not uſe to be ſo <hi>critically</hi> ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, whatever they may be at other times; but every mans fear is his own <hi>Pope,</hi> and can grant diſpenſations for matters of greater <hi>ſcruple</hi> then this can be: if any perſons can think themſelves ſecure or out of danger, not onely at this time, but at all times, ſo long as <hi>England</hi> is infeſted with ſuch <hi>Wolves</hi> and <hi>Tygers,</hi> it muſt be ſuch peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as either have no <hi>Religion,</hi> and ſo care not what is uppermoſt, but like empty clouds can ride upon any wind, and change into any form; or ſuch
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:51961:25"/>as deſire the <hi>Romiſh Religion</hi> may again prevail and be eſtabliſhed in theſe <hi>Nations;</hi> or elſe ſuch as are not ſenſible that the Doctrines and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of that <hi>Church</hi> teach and authorize, Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Rebellion, Murder, and the utter extirpation of all <hi>Heretiques,</hi> by all or any ways or methods whatſoever.</p>
            <p>To convince people of this, there is nothing more clear and evident, not onely from the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of private Doctors among them, but from ſeveral <hi>Bulls</hi> of former <hi>Popes,</hi> and from the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees</hi> of their <hi>Councils,</hi> which would be too long here to inſert, and are already notoriouſly known to all learned men; and for thoſe who want ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther opportunity or ability to peruſe their <hi>Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings,</hi> they may read enough in the Bloody <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bricks</hi> of their Actions to convince them of the reality as well as greatneſs of their danger, nor need they ſeek for Foreign <hi>Examples,</hi> who will not credit thoſe before given; our own Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and this <hi>City</hi> Renowned over all the habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table World, will afford the moſt unlettered Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple inſtances more then enough, both of former times, and yet freſh and bleeding <hi>date; Smith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> will never forget the cruel <hi>Bonfires</hi> of <hi>Queen Maries</hi> ſhort life and Reign; and what treatment our Fathers were to have received from the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Armada</hi> of <hi>Eighty Eight,</hi> had it proved more then an <hi>unluckly boaſt,</hi> the whips, chains, ſhackles, knives, daggers, and other Inſtruments of cruelty with which, and Savage Butchers that <hi>Navy</hi> made the <hi>Ocean</hi> groan, are certainly able to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:51961:26"/>inſtruct the dulleſt, or the weakeſt <hi>capacities.</hi> Nor are the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> grown more mild or gentle by the f equent diſappointments, which our merciful and gracious <hi>God</hi> had in compaſſion to us given them; but rather more furious and exaſperated: and ſince Heaven refuſes to favour their <hi>Treaſons,</hi> they have made a Covenant with <hi>Hell,</hi> and an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with <hi>Death</hi> to take their part. I will not repeat the confident, and beyond all former things audacious <hi>Murthers,</hi> which they have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, even ſince the diſcovery of their intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Conſpiracy;</hi> there is not a child in the Streets but can give a <hi>Narrative</hi> of the <hi>Tragedy:</hi> ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relenting and incorrigible are they even when the <hi>Rod of God</hi> is upon them, and ſo blinded with the <hi>rage</hi> of cruelty and revenge, that they will not ſee that the hand of <hi>God</hi> is gone out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them; and what would they do then, ſhould <hi>God</hi> permit them to ride in triumph over our heads? certainly their <hi>proud waters would have gone even over our ſoul, they would have ſwallowed us up quick when they were ſo wrathfully diſpleaſed at us.</hi> And whenever the bottom of this dark de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign ſhall be opened; when theſe chambers of <hi>Death</hi> and habitations of <hi>Cruelty</hi> ſhall be expoſed to the light of the <hi>Sun,</hi> which it is to be hoped a little time will do; the whole <hi>World</hi> ſhall be witneſs, that there is little reaſon to doubt a ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable of what I have written.</p>
            <p>There is but one thing more which at preſent I would propoſe to the <hi>Conſideration</hi> of People,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:51961:26"/>and eſpecially thoſe of this <hi>City,</hi> which is juſtly celebrated as the moſt noble <hi>Emporium</hi> or <hi>Mart</hi> of the <hi>World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That our greatneſs, ſtrength and power, our Riches and trade, and in a word, the well-being plenty and proſperity, as well as the Peace of our <hi>Nation,</hi> does in the greateſt meaſure depend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>Maritine ſtrength,</hi> there will not be found any who can deny. That this ſtrength at <hi>Sea,</hi> depends upon the encouragement and ſupport of <hi>Traffick</hi> and <hi>Navigation</hi> will likewiſe be agreed on all hands. That it is therefore and ought to be the deſign of every good Subject and <hi>Citizen</hi> as well as it is of the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Government,</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote theſe, will by an undeniable <hi>Conſequence</hi> follow from theſe premiſes.</p>
            <p>How invidiouſly all our <hi>Neighbours,</hi> eſpecially thoſe of the <hi>Roman Religion,</hi> look upon this great power of our <hi>Nation</hi> at <hi>Sea;</hi> and how ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful that <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Traffique</hi> which we maintain throughout the <hi>World</hi> is to them, is eaſily to be obſerved by their endeavouring to come in with us for a <hi>ſhare:</hi> they know little of the affairs of <hi>France,</hi> who do not take notice how induſtrious that <hi>Monarch</hi> and his great <hi>Ministers</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> and particularly <hi>Monſieur Colbert</hi> are, to encourage and extend the arms of their Foreign Trade, and to diſcourage all beſides the <hi>Natives</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and how <hi>Conſiderable</hi> within this few years they have have themſelves in compariſon of former times;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:51961:27"/>and whoever ſhall view the Ports of <hi>Thoulon, Marſeilles, Breſt, Rochel, &amp;c.</hi> And ſee them proud with their ſtately <hi>Caſtles</hi> of Wood, heretofore ſtrangers to the Tydes of <hi>France:</hi> whoſo ſhall withal reflect upon the actions of <hi>Tobago</hi> in the <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and <hi>Palermo</hi> in <hi>Sicily,</hi> where the <hi>Heer de Ruyter,</hi> who had ſaved <hi>Holland</hi> from the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>England</hi> fell under the riſing Arms of <hi>France:</hi> he that will bring theſe propoſitions together, ſhall be able to draw a <hi>Demonstrative concluſion</hi> from them, that <hi>France,</hi> will in a few Years ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle hard for the <hi>Dominion</hi> and Sovereignty of the <hi>Seas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor will they make any Scruple, if Intereſt did not animate them to it, upon the account, or at leaſt the pretence of <hi>Religion,</hi> to diſturb and weaken us <hi>Heretiques,</hi> in our <hi>Trade,</hi> and <hi>Naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> eſpecially in the <hi>Levant,</hi> where by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modiouſneſs of their <hi>Ports,</hi> they will have all the advantages to do it: and if once they come not to dread our power, or be able to grapple with us in the <hi>Streights,</hi> and make themſelves Maſters of that important place of ſtrength and ſituation <hi>Tangier,</hi> they will either totally exclude us if they can, or however come in with us for the greateſt ſhare of the Commerce of the <hi>Mediterranean;</hi> and if they ſhall gain their point ſo far, as to cut off one <hi>Limb</hi> of our <hi>Traffique,</hi> our Navigation and by conſequence our Power at <hi>Sea,</hi> will by degrees decline apace: and what we loſe, they will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gain; and if they arrive to that degree, to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:51961:27"/>ride <hi>Admirals</hi> of the <hi>Ocean,</hi> of neceſſity we ſhall be permitted only to truckle under them, and ſhall have juſt ſo much trade, as we ſteal, or they are not able to mannage.</p>
            <p>Now the moſt probable way that can be propoſed to ruine our <hi>Traffique</hi> and <hi>Navigation,</hi> and thereby to ſecure and increaſe their own; is to diſcourage Foreign <hi>Merchants,</hi> and oblige them to withdraw their <hi>Effects,</hi> and to ſtarve ours for want of Trade: for by this means they will in a few Years be able to give new <hi>Laws</hi> of <note n="*" place="margin">An Iſland in <hi>France,</hi> where the firſt Maritine Laws were made.</note>
               <hi>Oleron</hi> to the <hi>Seas.</hi> The ready way to Effect this, is to keep us in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>broyls</hi> among our ſelves: for what a <hi>damp</hi> muſt it of neceſſity give to all <hi>Merchants,</hi> both <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Foreigners</hi> to be in ſuch an inſecure Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they muſt have not onely the hazards and damages of <hi>Winds</hi> and <hi>Seas,</hi> Rocks and <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats</hi> to venture upon, but that they muſt be every moment in fear of ſuffering Shipwrack on the ſhoar? The <hi>Change</hi> I doubt not is ſufficiently ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of this truth at preſent; and if one ſees a full morning <hi>Change,</hi> it is more to barter news, then to drive bargains; and that trade brings in no <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms</hi> to the <hi>Crown,</hi> nor Riches to the <hi>Nation;</hi> and ſo long as we cannot be ſecure, but that by the treachery of theſe <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and <hi>Seminaries,</hi> our <hi>City</hi> may again be reduced to aſhes, our perſons ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly murdered, that we know not who to truſt, nay the <hi>Royal Perſon</hi> and Government deſtroyed in a moment, and mens <hi>Eſtates</hi> given to the ravage of the <hi>Murderers,</hi> what encouragement can <hi>Merchants</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:51961:28"/>have to trade? ſo long as there are ſo many poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous <hi>Spiders</hi> laying their cunning nets and <hi>toyles</hi> to take and deſtroy them: what courage can the Innocent and induſtrious <hi>Bees</hi> have to gather Hony for the <hi>Common Hive?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides it is worth our <hi>Conſideration,</hi> how de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenceleſs ſo great an <hi>Iſland</hi> as this is, and how li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Foreign Invaſions, and Depredations, if ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their own Shiping and <hi>Naval</hi> power decays, or does not exceed or at leaſt equal that of our <hi>Neighbours:</hi> and ſhould any of them grow ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent at <hi>Sea,</hi> as either out of <hi>Ambition,</hi> or <hi>Zeal</hi> to propagate the <hi>Catholique Religion</hi> to attempt an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion upon us; how dangerous is it to have a <hi>party</hi> within ready to joyn with them, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat a <hi>Conqueſt</hi> upon our Ruine?</p>
            <p>Aſſuredly, ſo long as there are ſo many <hi>Semi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries</hi> and <hi>Jeſuits</hi> among us, they will conſtantly be gaining <hi>Proſelytes</hi> among us to their own <hi>Church,</hi> and making factions and diviſions in ours: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as were we clear of them, we might hope in time the number of Papiſts would decreaſe, and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly many of the more ſimple and innocent <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts,</hi> ſtartled with the blackneſs of this horrid <hi>trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> or for fear of the penal <hi>Laws,</hi> will return to their <hi>Allegiance</hi> and <hi>duty;</hi> and many more would, if they were not buoy'd up by the imaginary dangers with which their <hi>Priests</hi> affright them, or encouraged by the meritoriouſneſs of that obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacy, in which they do all they can to confirm
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:51961:28"/>them: But ſo long as the <hi>Romiſh</hi> party can by our Diviſions ſhelter their <hi>Priests</hi> from diſcovery and the juſt puniſhment of the <hi>Laws,</hi> they will not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be confirmed in their pertinacy, but they will be always ready to receive ſuch impreſſions of <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyalty</hi> from them, and upon occaſion to throw off, not only all duty and <hi>Allegiance</hi> to their <hi>Sovereign,</hi> but all morality, and even <hi>humanity</hi> it ſelf, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and for the promoting of the <hi>Catholique Interest:</hi> and ſo long as we have ſo many ſorts of <hi>Protestant Diſſenters,</hi> who will not ſubmit to any certain way of Diſcovering who are <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and who are not; we muſt certainly be contented, whether we will or no, to have theſe <hi>Amorites</hi> and <hi>Jebuſites</hi> in our Land, <hi>as Goads in our ſides, and thorns in our Eyes:</hi> we muſt ſit down with our fears and dangers, and only have the feeble power to know and lament our <hi>miſery,</hi> but not to help it.</p>
            <p>To conclude, If either our Lives, our Liberties, our <hi>Religion,</hi> our <hi>Intereſt,</hi> our <hi>Duty</hi> or our Danger, the <hi>glory</hi> of our <hi>Nation,</hi> or the natural affection we owe to our <hi>Poſterity,</hi> have any power or <hi>Influence</hi> upon the people of theſe <hi>Nations,</hi> to be unanimous in detecting the <hi>Authors</hi> of our preſent fears, or fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture apprehenſions; they all call aloud upon eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y man, to uſe all lawful ways and means to clear them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the dreadful <hi>guilt</hi> of being <hi>Acceſſories</hi> and <hi>Confederates</hi> to our own, and the ruine of the <hi>Reformed Apostolick</hi> and truly <hi>Chriſtian Religion;</hi> and if nothing of all this will move the hearts of men to <hi>compaſſionate</hi> themſelves, <hi>God</hi> have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:51961:29"/>upon us! And if we muſt ſuffer, permit us <hi>to fall into his hands, for his mercies are great; l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t us not fall into the hands of Men,</hi> and of all Mankind, not into the hands of theſe Wicked and Blood-thirſty Men, whoſe Tender Mercies are Cruelty it ſelf.</p>
            <q>Exurgat Deus, diſſipentur inimici.</q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51961:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
